<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Meta | Zephyrizing]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.zephyrizing.net/blog/categories/meta/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.zephyrizing.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-20T22:27:27-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.zephyrizing.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Geoff Shannon]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[geoffpshannon@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Am I Doing This?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.zephyrizing.net/blog/2013/09/03/why-am-i-doing-this/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-03T03:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.zephyrizing.net/blog/2013/09/03/why-am-i-doing-this</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[It's weird, but I feel like I've been peer pressured into starting
this blog.  Not that anyone has ever said "Geoff, you really need to
start a blog."  It just seems like the thing to do.  More importantly,
it seems like you're less legitimate as a programmer if you DON'T have
a blog.  Particularly a blog where you write about cool
programming/tech things that you've discovered or figured out.

But here's the thing.  I'm still learning much more than I'm figuring
out on my own.  So I decided I would write about the one subject that
I am actually exploring on my own - seasoning cast iron cookware.

<!--more-->

A couple years ago when I was living in my first apartment with my
best friend Garrett, we bought some cast iron skillets.  We got them
from Lodge, because it seemed like the only company that really sold
cast iron anymore.  When we got them though, the factory seasoning was
somewhat disappointing, as was the quality of the metal itself.  In
particular, we noticed that the grain of the metal was quite large and
that this led to a very rough and almost pitted looking surface to the
metal.  Not exactly ideal.

I had used cast iron pans for years.  They were my favorite pans that
my mother owned.  I learned a bit about how to care for cast iron from
my mother.  Mainly, not to put them away wet.  Typically we would
towel dry, and then we would put them on the stove-top for a couple
minutes until they were completely dry.  When I got my own cast iron
however, I decided that I wanted to know more about how to really
properly care for cast-iron.  But I was sorely disappointed by the
collective knowledge that I found on the internet.  Most of it was
only half complete, or simply vague.  Some pages sounded more like
urban legend than actual advice.  I was recently told with great
conviction that the one thing you absolutely cannot do is submerge a
cast-iron pan in soapy water; as though this would cause it to shatter
instantly.

This has started to change.  In about ten seconds of googling today
(September 2013), I found one [blog post by Sheryl Canter][castchem]
that talks specifically about the chemistry of cast iron seasoning.
But at the time, the situation was exactly as Sheryl Canter describes,
lots of mutually conflicting information with very few common threads.

[castchem]: http://sherylcanter.com/wordpress/2010/01/a-science-based-technique-for-seasoning-cast-iron/

So Garrett and I extracted what wisdom we could from it, and basically
started experimenting.  Not terribly scientifically, but we both
anecdotally noted what we thought was effective about our various
endeavors, and ended up diverging in our methodology.  I became
partial to the coating with oil and then baking in the oven at high
heat, while Garrett went in the direction of stove-top seasoning.

More recently, I&#8217;ve come around to the stove-top seasoning method,
mostly because it&#8217;s super convenient - after you&#8217;re done cooking, just
put some oil in the pan, and turn the heat up a bit.

The biggest innovation so far has been using a flat-bladed metal
spatula to actively push the oil around while heating it on the
stove-top.  This has a couple of effects, but the biggest one is that
it actively enforces the surface of the pan to be fairly even as
seasoning builds up because the spatula mechanically removes seasoning
that is remarkably higher than other points.

The other big boon that I stumbled on by accident was using sunflower
seed oil.  I say by accident because it just happened that Trader
Joe&#8217;s carries a very cheap bottle of sunflower seed oil that we bought
to try out.  It turns out to be really nice and easy to cook with, and
also very good at seasoning my cast-iron.  After reading Sheryl&#8217;s blog
post, it&#8217;s clear that there&#8217;s a reason why when you look at this
[table of oil iodine values][iodine].  Sunflower seed oil is right up
there in the category of &#8220;semi-drying&#8221; oils.

[iodine]: http://www.journeytoforever.org/biodiesel_yield.html#highiodine

The other interesting point about my adventures in cast-iron seasoning
has been my unfortunate tendency to periodically simply burn the
seasoning right out of my pan.  This usually happens when I get
distracted in the middle of seasoning my pan and end up leaving it in
the oven at 500 degrees for four hours.  Most recently my girlfriend
and I left for the entire day (9+ hours) after I had turned on the
electric stove-top to medium in preparation for frying up some eggs
for breakfast (which didn&#8217;t happen).  So the pan slowly cooked it&#8217;s
way through the seasoning, and when I got back the bottom of the
skillet was nice and grey, and covered in a fine black dust.

I used to get really upset every time this happened. Now, I&#8217;ve come to
be much more Zen about it, and accept the impermanence of the
seasoning on my pan. Now, I sort of regard almost as an opportunity to
try to re-season it again.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
