<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rant | Zephyrizing]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.zephyrizing.net/blog/categories/rant/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.zephyrizing.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-20T22:27:27-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.zephyrizing.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Geoff Shannon]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[geoffpshannon@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[... And This Is Why Master Should Be Stable]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.zephyrizing.net/blog/2014/10/07/dot-dot-dot-and-this-is-why-master-should-be-stable/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-07T12:28:48-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.zephyrizing.net/blog/2014/10/07/dot-dot-dot-and-this-is-why-master-should-be-stable</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Second day at Hacker School.  I spent the morning doing two things:

- getting my blog setup to use [Octopress].
- helping another HS-er troubleshoot getting setup with [Flask] and [Flaskr].

[Octopress]: http://octopress.org/
[Flask]: http://flask.pocoo.org/
[Flaskr]: http://flask.pocoo.org/docs/0.10/tutorial/introduction/

<!--more-->

Yesterday, I was super frustrated by the difficulties I had in getting
Octopress going, and was reminded of the frustrations with setting up
Ruby environments that led me to wipe my computer and start from
scratch a few weeks ago.  You know, that and a certain amount of boredom.

Anyhow, I was able to make more headway today, largely because I
sorted out all of the really silly stuff yesterday.

But helping Sammy with setting up [Flask] was a nightmare!  TL;DR, we
figured it out, and it was incredibly simple.

First off, there were some minor SNAFU&#8217;s with me showing her about
[virtualenv], and explaining briefly how it works and how why she
should use it.  But then, we were confronted with these instructions
on the [Flaskr doc page][flaskr-github] on Github, a natural place to
look when the [&#8220;actual&#8221; docs][Flaskr] don&#8217;t mention anything about how
to install or setup the damn thing.

We spent nearly two and a half hours searching for the mythical
`flask` binary, to no avail.  Finally, after I inadvertently ran
aacross this [flask issue][issue], it dawned on me that we might be
having the same problem.  Well, that&#8217;s not quite true.  In reality, I
got so frustrated that I decided to just try the simplest thing that I
could think of to get flaskr to run `python flaskr.py`.  Low and
behold, it worked!!  Then, in retrospect, having seen that issue
describing the disconnect between the docs for flaskr in the flask
`master` branch and what the latest stable version was, I went and
looked at the [last stable release docs][laststable] for Flaskr, and
there it was. Simple instructions to do the simple, straightforward
thing.

[[virtualenv]: http://virtualenv.readthedocs.org/en/latest/virtualenv.html
[flaskr-github]: https://github.com/mitsuhiko/flask/tree/master/examples/flaskr
[issue]: https://github.com/mitsuhiko/flask/issues/1180
[laststable]: https://github.com/mitsuhiko/flask/tree/0.10.1/examples/flaskr
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
